# Mark Decker

Curriculum Vitae

Level 4 Mathews Building UNSW 2052 Sydney Australia \$\psi +61 (04) 016 00022 ⋈ m.decker@unsw.edu.au https://goo.gl/4Ldu3s ORCID id: 0000-0003-1071-611X

# Summary

I am a United States citizen working at the nexus of hydrology, atmospheric sciences, ecology, weather, and climate. I focus on developing and utilzing large scale hydrological, land surface, and climate models to address grand challenges relating to weather, climate, and water resources. I have over 900 total citations and experience developing courses and teaching both graduate and undergraduate students.

## Education

2006–2010 PhD Atmospheric Science, University of Arizona, Tucson, GPA - 4.00. 2003–2006 Ms Atmospheric Science, University of Arizona, Tucson, GPA - 4.00.

1999–2003 BS Engineering Mathematics, University of Arizona, Tucson, GPA - 3.78.

# Research Specialities

- Land surface model development, testing, and validation
- Climate model development and evaluation
- Large scale hydrological modeling
- Surface processes including land-atmosphere interactions, water, and energy
- Atmospheric processes including boundary layer responses to the land surface
- Utilizing observation products in novel ways to constrain models

#### Research Positions

2013-Present Research Fellow, University of New South Wales, Centre of Excellence in Climate System Science, Sydney, Australia.

> Developed the Australian land surface model with a focus on hydrology and land-atmosphere interactions.

- Developed a pore scale model of soil evaporation in collaboration with ETH-Zurich;
- o Formulated a groundwater model and parameterization for subgrid scale soil moisture processes including runoff:
- Demonstrated the necessity of using coupled simulations for projections of irrigation demand.

2010-2013 Postdoctoral Research Fellow, University of New South Wales, Climate Change Research Centre, Sydney, Austalia.

> Utilized remote sensing products and land surface models to quantify groundwater-transpiration variability in semiarid regions.

2003-2010 Research Assistant, University of Arizona, Tucson.

Derived novel numerical soluton to the non-linear partial differential equation governing soil water flow.

# **Teaching Positions**

2016–present **Course coordinator and lead lecturer**, *University of New South Wales*, Climate Change Research Centre, Sydney, Australia.

Taught undergraduate course 'Fundamentals of atmospheric science'.

Developed the course material, including lectures and assignments.

2012–2015 **Co-coordinator and lecturer**, *University of New South Wales*, Climate Change Research Centre, Sydney, Australia.

Taught sections of the undergraduate courses 'Fundamentals of atmospheric science'.

Taught sections of the undergraduate courses 'Climate System Science'.

Developed the course material, including lectures and assignments.

2007–2010 **Teaching Assistant**, *University of Arizona*, Department of Atmospheric Sciences, Tucson, Arizona.

Taught graduate level course when professor was traveling. Graded Assignments.

#### Service

- American Geophysical Union
- American Meteorological Society
- Australian Atmospheric and Oceanographic Society
- Leader of the land group at the Climate Change Research Centre
- Reviewer for Journal of Climate, Journal of Hydrometeorology, Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems

### Publications

- o Total Citations 964. Top four papers have 670, 116, 74, and 35. H index 7
- Decker, M., S. Ma, and A.J. Pitman (2016) Local land-atmosphere feedbacks limit irrigation demand, Environmental Research Letters, submitted.
- Decker, M., D. Or., A.J. Pitman, and A.M. Ukkola (2016) New turbulent resistance parameterization for soil evaporation based on a pore scale model: impact on surface fluxes in CABLE, *Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems*, accepted.
- Ukkola, A., M.G. De Kauwe, A.J. Pitman, M.J. Best, G. Abramowitz, V. Haverd, M. Decker, N Haughton, (2016)
   Land surface models systematically overestimate the intensity, duration and magnitude of seasonal-scale evaporative droughts, *Environmental Ressearch Letters*, in press.
- Ukkola, A., A.J. Pitman, M. Decker, M.G. De Kauwe, G. Abramowitz, J. Kala, and Y.P. Wang, (2016) Modelling evapotranspiration during precipitation deficits: identifying critical processes in a land surface model, *Hydrology* and *Earth System Science*, 20, 2403-2419.
- Decker, M., A.J. Pitman, and J. Evans, (2015) Diagnosing the seasonal land–atmosphere correspondence over northern Australia: dependence on soil moisture state and correspondence strength definition, *Hydrology and Earth System Science*, 19, 3433-3447, doi:10.5194/hess-19-3433-2015.
- Decker, M., (2015) Development and evaluation of a new soil moisture and runoff parameterization for the CABLE LSM including subgrid-scale processes, *Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems*, 7, 1788-1809, doi:10.1002/2015MS000507.
- Kala, J., M. Decker, J.F. Exbrayat, A.J. Pitman, C. Carouge, J. Evans, and G. Abramowitz (2014) Influence of leaf area index prescriptions on simulations of heat, moisture, and carbon fluxes, *Journal of Hydrometeorology*, 15, 448-503.

- Decker, M., A.J. Pitman, and J. Evans, (2014) Applying scaled vegetation greenness metrics to constrain simulated transpiration anomalies: a study over Australia, *Journal of Hydrometeorology*, 15, 1607–1623, doi:10.1175/JHM-D-13-070.1.
- Kala, J., J.P. Evans, A.J. Pitman, C.B. Schaaf, M. Decker, C. Carouge, D. Mocko, and Q. Sun, (2014), Implementation of a soil albedo scheme in the CABLEv1.4b land surface model and evaluation against MODIS estimates over Australia, *Geoscientific Model Development*, 7, 2121-2140, doi:10.5194/gmd-7-2121-2014.
- Decker, M., A.J. Pitman, and J. Evans, (2013) Groundwater constraints on simulated transpiration variability over Southeastern Australian forests, *Journal of Hydrometeorology*, 14, 534–559, doi:10.1175/JHM-D-12-058.1.
- Decker, M., M.A. Brunke, K. Sakaguchi, X. Zeng, and M. Bisolovich, (2012), Evaluation of the reanalysis products from GSFC, NCEP, and ECMWF using flux tower observations, *Journal of Climate*, 25, 1916–1944, doi:10.1175/JCLI-D-11-00004.1.
- Wang, Z., X. Zeng, M. Decker, (2010), Improving snow processes in the Noah land model, Journal of Geophysical Ressearch, 115, 2156–2202, doi::10.1029/2009JD013761.
- Zeng, X., and M. Decker., (2010), Reply to Improving the Numerical Solution of Soil Moisture-Based Richards Equation for Land Models with a Deep or Shallow Water Table, *Journal of Hydrometeorology*, 11, 1051–1054, DOI: 10.1175/2010JHM1199.1.
- Oleson, K., et al., M. Decker, (2010), Technical Description of version 4.0 of the Community Land Model (CLM), NCAR/TN-478+STR, NCAR TECHNICAL NOTE.
- Decker, M. and X. Zeng, (2009), Impact of modified Richards equation on global soil moisture simulation in the Community Land Model (CLM3.5), *Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems*, 1, 5, 22 pp, doi:10.3894/JAMES.2009.1.5.
- Zeng, X., and M. Decker., (2009), Improving the numerical solution of soil moisture-based Richards equation for land models with a deep or shallow water table, *Journal of Hydrometeorology*, 10, 308–319, doi:10.1175/2008JHM1011.1.
- **Decker, M.**, and X. Zeng, (2006), An empirical formulation of soil ice fraction based on in situ observations, *Geophysical Research Letters*, 33, L05402, doi:10.1029/2005GL024914.

## References

## Andy Pitman

Director
COE ARCSS
University of New South Wales
Sydney, Australia
a.pitman@unsw.edu.au
+61-2-9385-7075

### Xubin Zeng

Professor
Department of Atmospheric Sciences
University of Arizona
Tucson, Arizona
xubin@atmo.arizona.edu
+1-520-621-4782

#### Dani Or

Professor

Soil and Terrestrial Environmental Physics ETH Zurich dani.or@env.ethz.ch +41-44-633-60-15

#### Jason Evans

Associate Professor Climate Change Research Centre University of New South Wales Sydney, Australia jason.evans@unsw.edu.au +61-2-9385-7066